Hello, welcome to this presentation of the MOOC "Introduction to Galois Theory"
MOOC, or FLOT, for "Formation en Ligne Ouverte a Tous", in Moliere's language
Solving polynomial equations with a degree <= 4 has been achievable by mathematicians since XVI-th century
For example in this second degree equation, we have
a root : [ 1/2 + 1/2 j sqrt(3) ] that is a typical standard resolution based on the discriminant (here -3)
In this 3rd-degree example,
here the real root only involves cubic and square root operations, as well as, of course, the 4 arithmetic operations
let us look at a very simple degree-4 equation
we will use a free software named sage, that I recommend to use
that turned out extremely efficient
so what do we find ?
well, depending on the taste, a beautiful or ugly formula
that involves the 4 operations, nested n-th roots
here cubic and square roots
we will see as an exercise that these equations with a degree <= 4 can be solved
you will be taught how to, the way mathematicians know how to do that for a very long time
so what happens with degrees >= 5 ?
for that let us consider 3 typical examples
first example is very simple, low degree, simple coefficients
second example, still low degree, but more complex coefs
finally third example, really complicated with a high degree (9), and many non-null coefs
What questions can we ask ourselves ?
are we able to solve these equations using only the 4 operations, and nested roots
and if so, which is the simplest to solve, which is the hardest
like earlier, we use sage, some good publicity for this very nice software
let us see
you can see here the 3 equations in question
for the most complicated one, there is a cubic root here
and here a power of a cubic root, and a square root
so we have a solution with nested radicals
the second equation, a little simpler, and here again we have a solution that involves only  square roots
so here again solutions can be expressed as nested radicals
for the last one, apparently the simplest, sage does not know how to handle it, that's why it just copies the input equation
simply because there is no such formula, like Galois's theory will explain
so we can see that the simplest of these 3 equations
is not solvable with nested radicals
while more complex equations are solvable this way, including the one with a high degree and complex coefs
the order of complexity of these equations is unexpected
since it is (2) < (3) < (1) which is counter-intuitive
so Galois's theory can explain what is happening here, and you will be taught how to define Galois groups
how to compute them, and how to understand all these phenomena
So let us explain, what is intuitively this Galois group ?
the key concept is the notion of symetry, symetry within C the field of complex numbers,  that preserves the 4 operations
these symetries shuffle the roots of any polynomial equation
so this is a set of permutations of these n roots
and these permutations make the Galois group of this equation
to get an intuitive grasp on this notion, let us have a little quizz
on a very concrete example
let us look at the first, apparently simplest, equation
using a calculus software, or using our future skills
this group is generated by two elements
two permutations of the 5 roots z1..z5
(1) a cyclic permutation among the 5 roots
(2) a transposition that swaps z1 and z2
we will see how to compute the group generated by (1) and (2)
and will see this is the set of all permutations, it has 120 elements, and somehow rather complex
The second equation has a Galois group generated by a single element
a cyclic permutation of 4 of the 5 roots, one of the roots is a singularity, we call it z5
this is simply because there is an "obvious" root, namely -1
which is a rational number, and these are always fixed by the Galois group
this is why we only have 4 of the 5 roots involved in the permutations; this is a very simple group
as for the last and third equation, we again have a group generated by a single cyclic permutation of the 9 roots
So let us summarize; the Galois group for equation (2), low degree but complex coefs,
is a commutative, cyclic group,  with a very small cardinal (4)
Equation (3), apparently the hardest, high degree, many coefs,
gives a commutative, cyclic, very simple group, with a slightly larger cardinal (9), so a bit more complex than G2
and equation (1), apparently the simplest, gives a group that is not commutative,
very large (cardinal 120), and we will see that it is non-solvable in the sense of the group theory
hence the counter-intuitive order of complexity among the equations (2) < (3) < (1)
I thank you for attending this presentation, and look forward to seeing you on the first real lecture of this MOOC
that will by given by Olivier, but you can start exchanging in the chat rooms with your co-FLOTers
ask your questions to the staff, in any case see you soon, and wish you a good work